Marcel Breuer Papers
Marcel Breuer Papers
- Project records
  - CONVENT OF THE SISTERS OF DIVINE PROVIDENCE, Baldegg, Switzerland (1968-1976). Marcel Breuer, Robert F. Gatje and Mario Jossa, Architects; Beat A.H. Jordi, Associated Architect; Beat von Segesser, Associated Architect. [Religious], (Alternate names: Baldegg Convent; Infirmary and Old Mother's Ho
    - Photographs, 72
      - Concrete ceiling construction, construction, interior view; black and white photographs; 2 (Box 134, Folder 15)
      - Exterior view, construction; color photographs; 15 (Box 134, Folder 15)
      - Religious statuary, color photographs; 5 (Box 134, Folder 15)
      - Old Sisters' Home, construction, exterior view; color photographs; 4 (Box 134, Folder 15)
      - Various exterior views and details, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 22 (Box 134, Folder 15)
      - Ground level plan with legend, drawings, plan; photocopy; 1 (Box 134, Folder 15)
  - CORK EXHIBITION, Berlin, Germany (1931). Marcel Breuer, Architect. [Exhibition], (Alternate names: Korkindustrie Austellung); See also Bauausstellung.
    - Drawings, 5
      - Korkindustrie (Nr. 444) [Leaf 365] (19 Apr 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 9)
      - Fussbodenplan (Nr. 444a) [Leaf 366] (22 Apr 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 5)
      - Kork- und Fotos (Nr. 445) [Leaf 367] (22 Apr 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Map-case 75)
      - Landkarte (Nr. 446) [Leaf 368a] (22 Apr 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Map-case 75)
      - Tisch für Apparate (Nr. 447) [Leaf 367a] (22 Apr 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 3)
    - Photographs, 1
      - Exhibition installation, finished project, interior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 119, Folder 10)
  - COSTON HOUSE, Oldfield Lane, Greenford, England (Apr-Sep 1937) (not built). Marcel Breuer and F.R.S. Yorke, Architects. [Interior], (Alternate names: Shatsow House)
    - Project files
      - Correspondence, F.R.S. Yorke, J. Shastow (Box 120, Folder 12)
  - COUNTRY CLUB OF PURCHASE, Westchester, NY (1960-1963) (not built). Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects; Francis J. Duane, Golf Course Architect. [Recreational], (Alternate names: Purchase Hills; Brae Burn Country Club)
    - Drawings, 41
      - Aerial site photo (2 Mar 1960), site surveys (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1469)
      - Survey (20 Dec 1962), site surveys (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1469)
      - Golf course, preliminary plan B (3 Apr 1963) (Francis J. Duane, Golf Course Architect), presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1469)
      - Golf Course. Preliminary plan C (29 Apr 1963) (Francis J. Duane, Golf Course Architect), presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1469)
      - Presentation set, The Country Club of Purchase, Purchase Hills Realty Associates, Schulman-Pack (3 May-7 May 1963): Entrance elevation, site plan, floor plans, north elevation at face of building, west elevation at face of building, presentation drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1469)
      - Site plan and floor plans (3 May 1963), design development drawings (reproductions); 3 sheets with color annotations; 3 (Tube 1469)
      - Entrance elevation, west elevation and north elevation, design development drawings (reproductions); 3 (Tube 1469)
      - Design development sketches and drawings, design development drawings (originals); includes interior-exterior elevations, plans and site work; 25 (Tube 1469)
  - CRALL HOUSE, Gates Mills, OH (1953) (not built). Marcel Breuer, Architect. [Residential, Single]
    - Drawings, 38
      - Preliminary elevations (20 Nov 1953), presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 647)
      - Presentation set, pre-preliminary (25 Sep 1953): Dwg. Nos. 1-2, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 647)
      - Presentation set, preliminary (9 Dec 1953-12 Jan 1954), presentation drawings (originals); 8 (Tube 647)
      - Gross square foot area (10 Jan 1955), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 647)
      - Exterior door details (Dwg. No. SK-1) (13 Aug 1954), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 647)
      - Outside stair along north wall of garage (21 Sep 1954), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 647)
      - Supplementary details, working drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 647)
      - Bathroom and cabinet work, design development drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 647)
      - Construction set (19 Mar 1954-24 Aug 1954): Dwg. Nos. 1-10, 2E, working drawings (originals); 11 (Tube 647)
      - Curtain plan (19 Mar 1954), working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 647)
      - Elevations (19 Mar 1954), working drawings (reproductions); annotated print; 1 (Tube 647)
      - Painting and finishing plan (19 Mar 1954), working drawings (hybrid); annotated print with color samples attached; 1 (Tube 647)
      - Electrical layout (19 Mar 1954), working drawings (hybrid); annotated print; 1 (Tube 647)
      - Air conditioning plans (Dwg. No. —1) (3 Aug 1954), working drawings (reproductions); annotated print; 1 (Tube 647)
    - Project files
      - Correspondence: Client (18 Dec 1953), James Crall (Box 88, Folder 8)
  - DE BIJENKORF DEPARTMENT STORE COMPLEX, Rotterdam, Netherlands (1953-1957). Marcel Breuer and A. Elzas, Architects; Daniel Schwartzman, Consultant. [Commercial], See also De Bijenkorf Department Store Parking Garage.
    - Drawings, 177
      - Perspective rendering of elevation at corner, alternate scheme, presentation drawings (reproductions); photostat; 1 (Oversize 15)
      - Construction set (18 Nov 1954-16 Dec 1954): Kelder (1); Beganegrond (2); Tussenverdieping (3); 1st Verdieping (4); 2nd Verdieping (5); 3rd Verdieping (6); 4th Verdieping (7); DAK (8); Dwarsdoorsnede Tussen Syst. 8 and 9 (9); Langsdoorsnede Tussen Syst. C en D (10); Zvidgevel (12); Westgevel en Dwarsdoorsneden Tussen Syst. 2 en 3 and Syst. 1 en 2 (13); Noordgevel en Dwarsdoorsnede Tussen Syst. 4 en 5 (14); Langsdoorsnede Tussen Syst. H en G (15); Situatie (16), working drawings (originals); in Dutch; 15 (Tube 1069)
      - Furniture and fixtures details, schedules, lighting plans and details, store displays, Cineac theatre details, Quick Lunch Bar, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); 86 (Tube 1071)
      - Construction field office sketches (Aug 1953 - Feb 1954): Preliminary plans, sections, elevations and details, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); 21 (Tube 1072)
      - Preliminary plans, sections, and details (May - Jul 1954), design development drawings (originals); includes drawings for model maker; 20 (Tube 1072)
      - Floor plans, Ceiling plans (Dec 1954 - Aug 1955), design development drawings (originals); 7 (Tube 1072)
      - Undated sketches of plans and elevations, design development drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1072)
      - Elevation/façade renderings, presentation drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1072)
      - Ceiling plans (Aug-Sep 1955), design development drawings (reproductions); 3 (Tube 1096)
      - Programmatic zoning plans (May 1954), design development drawings (reproductions); 6 (Tube 1096)
      - Floor layout plans (1955) [Dutch], working drawings (reproductions); 4 (Tube 1096)
      - Electrical and lighting plan for Macy's White Plains expansion (Jul 1953) (Daniel Schwartzman, Architect), other drawings (reproductions); 8 (Tube 1096)
    - Published material
      - "Almacenes, en Rotterdam," Instituto Técnico De La Construcción Y Del Cemento (Apr 1956), reprint, 4 pgs.; in Spanish (Box 88, Folder 9)
      - "Architect Marcel Breuer... " Het Parool (Amsterdam) (16 Mar 1954), newspaper clipping; in Dutch (Box 88, Folder 10)
      - "'De Bijenkorf' te Rotterdam " Bouwkundig Weekblad (24 Apr 1956), tear sheet, pgs. 189-194; in Dutch (Box 88, Folder 9)
      - "Estados Unidos De Norteamerica - 1957," Integral (Aug 1957), tear sheet, 1 pg.; in Spanish (Box 88, Folder 9)
      - "Grand magasin à Rotterdam", tear sheet, 5 pgs.; in French (Box 88, Folder 9)
      - "Netherlands Department Store Rebuilds" Architectural Record (May 1955), reprint, pgs. 205-208 (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Photographs, 62
      - Elevation at corner with sculpture, model; copy negative; 1 (Oversize 15)
      - Model, black and white photograph; 1 (Box 88, Folder 11)
      - Excavation and foundation work, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 4 (Box 88, Folder 11)
      - Construction field office, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 13 (Box 88, Folder 11)
      - Model view [Slide 144], model; color slides; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of Gabo sculpture and building elevation [Slide 504], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Partial building elevation [Slide 505], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Construction field office in context [Slide 506], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of elevation with Cineac entrance [Slide 507], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Elevation with glass curtain wall [Slide 508], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View from above of store in context [Slide 509], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of Cineac entrance [Slide 511], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of Henry Moore Sculpture on upper level terrace [Slide 512], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Merchandise display case [Slide 513], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Exterior space sculpture prior to installation [Slide 514], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of elevation with Gabo Sculpture [Slide 528], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of two elevations at exterior corner [Slide 529], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of construction field office and elevation beyond [Slide 530], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of two model elevations at corner from above [Slide 531], model; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of two model elevations at corner [Slide 532], model; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View through staggered windows [Slide 533], finished project, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Parking entrance ramp and building façade [Slide 534], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of glass-enclosed pavilion and building elevation [Slide 535], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Exterior space sculpture prior to installation [Slide 536], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of building façade at corner [Slide 537], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Night view of exterior space sculpture in place [Slide 538], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Exterior space sculpture in the process of installation [Slide 539], finished project, exterior view; black and white slides; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View out from entrance hall [Slide 540], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Night view of exterior space sculpture and elevation [Slide 541], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of sign at main entrance [Slide 542], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Night view of illuminated sign at main entrance [Slide 543], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Night view of elevation with illuminated sign / windows [Slide 544], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of construction field office from above [Slide 545], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of main entrance doors with custom handles [Slide 546], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of entrance vestibule [Slide 547], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of glass pavilion and building elevation [Slide 548], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of site model with context [Slide 549], model; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of illuminated model elevations at corner [Slide 550], model; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Elevation [Slide 551], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of glass pavilion under construction [Slide 552], finished project, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - View of glass pavilion under construction [Slide 553], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Construction progress on glass pavilion [Slide 598], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Construction field office in context [Slide 773], construction, exterior view; color slide (duplicate of Slide 506); 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View of Cineac entrance with Gabo Sculpture installation [Slide 774], construction, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View of plaza with Gabo Sculpture installation [Slide 775], construction, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View of elevation with Gabo Sculpture installation [Slide 776], construction, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View of Gabo Sculpture installation [Slide 777], construction, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
  - DE BIJENKORF DEPARTMENT STORE PARKING GARAGE, Rotterdam, Netherlands (1970-1972). Marcel Breuer and Robert F. Gatje, Architects. [Commercial]
    See also De Bijenkorf Department Store Complex.
    - Drawings, 38
      - Composite plan, elevation studies, area calculations, design development drawings (originals); 8 (Tube 1121)
      - Alternate schemes: Scheme B (10 Apr 1970) (Dwg. nos. 1-3); Scheme C (10 Apr 1970) (Dwg. nos. 1-5); Scheme D (7 Aug 1970); 1 unnumbered, design development drawings (originals); 9 (Tube 1121)
      - Presentation set (14 Sep 1970) (Nos. 1-6): Plans, elevations, sections, presentation drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1121)
      - Presentation sheets (Feb - Mar 1971 and revisions May 1972): Plans, elevations, sections, details, presentation drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1121)
      - Presentation set (25 Feb 1972) (Nos. 5-9, 6A): Elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1121)
      - Presentation sheets: Elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1121)
      - Perspective rendering (17 Aug 1972), presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1121)
  - DE FRANCESCO APARTMENT, Berlin, Germany (1931). Marcel Breuer, Architect. [Interior]
    - Drawings, 10
      - Grundriss Rudolstätterstr. 9 (Nr. 395) [Leaf 326a] (24 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 25)
      - Schreibtisch (Nr. 396) [Leaf 327a] (24 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 25)
      - Schrankwand (Nr. 397) [Leaf 328a] (25 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 9)
      - Bettwand (Nr. 398) [Leaf 329] (25 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 4)
      - Schrankwand Wohnz (Nr. 399) [Leaf 330a] (26 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Map-case 75)
      - Bücherwand (Nr. 400) [Leaf 331a] (26 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 9)
      - Tisch (Nr. 401) [Leaf 332a] (26 Jan 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 3)
      - Ahorn Natur Mattiert (Nr. 409) [Leaf 340a] (5 Feb 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 3)
      - Ablegeplatten im Vorraum (Nr. 410) [Leaf 341a] (10 Feb 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 3)
      - Bettbügel (Nr. 411) [Leaf 342a] (20 Feb 1931), working drawing (originals); in German; 1 (Oversize 25)
    - Published material, See Professional Papers: Scrapbooks and clippings: Blue scrapbook (1).
    - Photographs, 7
      - Bedroom, finished project, interior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 119, Folder 11)
      - Bedroom [Slide 346 ], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Bedroom and study-living-dining room [Slide 735], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Bedroom wall cabinets, finished project, interior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 119, Folder 11)
      - Bedroom wall cabinets, two views [Slide 237], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
      - Study / living room, finished project, interior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 119, Folder 11)
      - Study / living room [Slide 680], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-2)
  - DE GUNZBURG CHALETS, Megève, France (1963-1964) (not built). Marcel Breuer, Architect. [Residential, Single]
    - Project files
      - Correspondence: Architects (1964), Robert F. Gatje (Box 128, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence: Client (1963-1964), Baron Alain de Gunzburg (Box 128, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous (1963), advisory in French from Construction ministry; business card from French architect (Box 128, Folder 10)
  - DEFENSE HOUSING, Wethersfield, CT (1942) (not built). Marcel Breuer, Architect. [Residential, Multi], (Alternate names: Wethersfield Project); See also Aluminum City Terrace.
    - Project files
      - Correspondence: Client (Jan-Mar 1942), FWA/NHA (Box 85, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence: Contractors and manufacturers (Jan 1942) (Box 85, Folder 2)
      - Office records, rough sketches, preliminary cost estimates, office correspondence, receipts and site sketch (Box 85, Folder 3)
      - Specifications, government issued standards/specifications for defense housing (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, EDUCATION AND WELFARE (HEW), HEADQUARTERS (HUBERT H. HUMPHREY FEDERAL BUILDING), Washington, DC (1960-1984 inclusive, 1967-1977 bulk). Marcel Breuer and Herbert Beckhard, Architects; Nolen-Swinburne and Associates, Architects. [Government], (Alternate names: FOB; HEW; Hubert H. Humphrey Building; South Portal Building; United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) headquarters building. )
    - Drawings, 574
      - Feasability study (25 Aug 1960): Sheet Nos. 1-10, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); set of originals and print set, multiples of some sheets; 23 (Tube 1216)
      - Air Rights Building (Feb 1968) (David Volkert and Assoc.): Site plan, design development drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1229)
      - Alternate scheme (3 Jun 1967): Situation plan, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); 1 original and 1 print; 1 (Tube 1229)
      - Diagrammatic study: South portal site (20 Feb 1968): Sheet Nos. 20-1 to 20-9, presentation drawings (reproductions); 10 (Tube 1229)
      - Sections (9 Feb 1968): Sections A-A to D-D, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); 4 originals and 7 prints, multiples of some sheets; 11 (Tube 1229)
      - South ventilation facility (circa Apr 1968) (David Volkert and Assoc.): Plans, elevations, sections, details, working drawings (reproductions); 28 (Tube 1229)
      - South ventilation facility: Isometric above grade and isometric below grade, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); 1 original and 2 prints; 3 (Tube 1229)
      - Preliminary set: Air Rights Building II (24 Jan 1968): Sheet Nos. P-1 to P-7, design development drawings (originals); 8 (Tube 1229)
      - Electrical room egress alternative (30 Apr 1968), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1229)
      - Egress: Water fountain, FHC, toilets (15 Jan 1968), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1229)
      - Air Rights Building: Plan (5 Jan 1967): Plan, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1229)
      - Feasability study, Air Rights Building (21 Apr 1966), presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1229)
      - Site plan (30 Jun 1966): Dwg. No. FSS-30, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1230)
      - Preliminary set (Jan-Feb 1967): Dwg. Nos. TSK1-TSK22, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); 4 originals, 4 prints; incomplete; 8 (Tube 1230)
      - Preliminary site plans and details (31 Aug 1970): Dwg. Nos. 2-1 to 2-8, design development drawings (originals); 8 (Tube 1230)
      - Tentative sketches (20 Mar 1961): Structural (Dwg. Nos. 21-23 to 21-30), design development drawings (reproductions); 8 (Tube 1230)
      - Typical column locations (10 Jun 1966), design development drawings (reproductions); Sverdrup and Parcel; 1 (Tube 1230)
      - Revised highway alignment scheme 'H' and basement plan diagram (9 May 1966), design development drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1230)
      - Design development drawings and sketches (Feb 1969-Apr 1970): SK-WD1 to SK-WD131; SK116-SK205, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); incomplete, some unnumbered; includes pre-cast concrete details, core plans, garage and parking studies, interior plan studies and perspectives, elevations and facade studies, isometrics of building corners, garage and tunnel studies, interior and exterior details, sample granite panels; 62 originals and 23 prints; 85 (Tube 1231)
      - Design development drawings and sketches (Jul 1973-Oct 1976): WSK-104 to WSK-146, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); incomplete and unnumbered; includes sign details, walkway color designs, fine arts proposal, visitor information center, lobby plans and details, terrace details, interior and exterior details; 33 originals and 10 prints; 43 (Tube 1232)
      - Partial tentative sketches (30 Apr 1968): Architectural (21-1 to 21-12); structural (21-13 to 21-23), working drawings (originals); 23 (Tube 1221)
      - Tentative sketches (circa 1969) (Sverdrup and Parcel): Structural (21-201 to 21-216), working drawings (reproductions); 16 (Tube 1222)
      - Tentative sketches (29 May 1969) (Joseph R. Loring and Associates): Mechanical-electrical (21-301 to 21-313), working drawings (reproductions); 13 (Tube 1222)
      - Tentative sketches (29 May 1969) (Joseph R. Loring and associates): Mechanical-electrical (21-401 to 21-410, 21-500 to 21-515), working drawings (reproductions); 26 (Tube 1223)
      - Completed tentative sketches (29 May 1969): Dwg. Nos. 21-101 to 21-141, working drawings (reproductions); incomplete; 36 (Tube 1224)
      - Tentative sketches (circa 1969): Lighting (E509 to E515), working drawings (reproductions); 7 (Tube 1224)
      - Construction set (31 Aug 1970): Architectural (5-1 to 5-62), working drawings (originals); marked "final revision, 1 Oct 1970"; most annotated; some duplicates; 65 (Tube 1225)
      - Executive conference room, audiovisual projection plan (12 Apr 1974): Dwg. No. 509-1, working drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1226)
      - HEW executive areas (18 Oct 1974): Dwg. Nos. CD-1 and CD-5, working drawings (hybrids); 2 (Tube 1226)
      - Conference room and interior details (9 Dec 1969-31 Aug 1970): Architectural (5-38 to 5-59), working drawings (originals and reproductions); incomplete and unnumbered sheets; 17 (Tube 1226)
      - Executive suites and conference room (10 Feb 1975): Architectural (11-A-1 to 11-A-11), working drawings (originals); some duplicates; 12 (Tube 1226)